Guide to the Ebenezer Alfred Johnson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Series III FINANCIAL AND LEGAL contains correspondence on financial and legal matters and other business and legal papers. Series III is housed in Boxes 14-16, folders 310-366. The correspondence part of Series III, folders 310-324, deals exclusively with Ebenezer Alfred Johnson's business activities. In the subject files, however, folders 325-366, other family members are represented, the most important being Alfred's father Ebenezer Johnson, Fanny Johnson, and brother-in-law DeWitt C. Morris. Business dealings with George H. Brown, the Van Cleves, and DeWitt C. Morris are outlined in Series I, but those with cousins William A. Law, a New Haven storekeeper, and Henry W. Law are delineated in Series III. Alfred rented property in New Haven, lent money to relatives, and owned stock in several mining companies. Although a professor and scholar of some note, Johnson kept his feet planted firmly in the business world and his not inconsiderable assets were increased by property that came from each wife.
Series IV GENEALOGY is found in Boxes 17 and 18, folders 367-395. It contains the genealogical research and correspondence of Charles Andrew Johnson. After retiring, Charles devoted a major proportion of his remaining twenty years to studying the history of his family. Correspondence between him and members of his family on this subject is found in Series I and Series II, but other correspondence plus extensive genealogical notes are located here. Perhaps the best known correspondent is Charles J. Hoadly (1828-1900), the Connecticut antiquarian and historian. Following chronologically arranged correspondence, Johnson's genealogical research on different family lines is found. It is filed alphabetically. The greatest volume of research notes is on the Johnson and Law families. The series includes two Johnson Family Ancestral Tablets and copies of funeral orations delivered after the death of Connecticut Governor Jonathan Law, Charles' great-great grandfather.
Series V contains about forty photographs, mostly unidentified, housed in Box 19. The persons tentatively or positively identified are Margaret (Van Cleve) Johnson, Harriet (Gilley) Johnson, Frances Henrietta Johnson, Alfred Van Cleve Johnson, and Charlotte (Morris) Houghton.
The Ebenezer Alfred Johnson (1813-1891) Family Papers came to Yale in two different parts at two separate times. The letters from several members of the Gibbs family came from Alfred Van Cleve Dasburg, son of Grace Mott Johnson and Andrew Dasburg and great-grandson of Ebenezer Alfred Johnson, in 1952, while the bulk of the papers came from Dasburg's estate in 1980. This collection of papers is related to two others, the Grace Mott Johnson Papers located at Beinecke Rare Books Library and the Gibbs Family Papers (Manuscript Group No. 236). All correspondence to and from Grace Mott Johnson is in the Grace Mott Johnson Papers, but information about her childhood can be found in the letters of her parents. The Gibbs Family Papers contain primarily eighteenth century material plus a small amount of nineteenth century business papers.
Some letters were annotated in pencil, probably by Alfred Dasburg before their coming to Yale, usually by a single word like "Gibbs" or "slaves." These markings are not enclosed in brackets.
Biographical / Historical
Ebenezer Alfred Johnson: admitted to the Connecticut bar, 1837; appointed professor of Latin at the University of the City of New York, 1838, and taught there for the rest of his career.
Biographical / Historical
The collection is open for research.
Brothers and sisters; Childbirth; Courtship; Death; Families; Frontier and pioneer life -- Michigan; Frontier and pioneer life -- Wisconsin; Pioneers -- Wisconsin; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; Educators; Adler, G. J. (George J.), 1821-1868; Andrews, E. A. (Ethan Allen), 1787-1858; Brown, Isaac V. (Isaac Van Arsdale), 1784-1861; Codman, Martha Ann Gilley, 1813-1875; Codman, William, 1795-1848; Daveiss, Louisa Elizabeth Van Cleve; Day, George Edward, 1815-1905; Delsfield, Richard, 1799-1863; Este, D. K. (David Kirkpatrick), 1785-1875; Este, Eliza P. Houston; Ferris, Isaac, 1798-1873; Firch, Susan, 1800-1846; Frelinghuysen, Theodore, 1787-1862; Geisse, Antoinette; Gibbs, Emily, 1841-1864; Gibbs, J. Willard (Josiah Willard), 1839-1903; Gibbs, Josiah W. (Josiah Willard), 1790-1861; Gibbs, Mary Anna Van Cleve; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Houston, Churchill, d. 1845; Houston, William Churchill, approximately 1746-1788; Janin, Louis, 1803-1874; Johnson, Alfred Van Cleve, 1847-1938; Johnson, Charles Andrew, 1818-1896; Johnson, E. A. (Ebenezer Alfred), 1813-1891; Johnson, Ebenezer, 1774-1863; Johnson, Ellen Marcia Doty, 1855-1932; Johnson, Frances Henrietta Gibbs, 1825-1845; Johnson, Harriett Gilley, 1820-1881; Johnson, Henrietta, 1845-1920; Johnson, Laura Mott, d. 1884; Johnson, Margaret Fox Van Cleve, 1820-1849; Johnson, Mary Ann, 1810-1877; Johnson, Sarah Bryan, 1812-1890; Johnson, Sidney Law, 1808-1887; Johnston, John Taylor, 1820-1893; Kingsley, James Luce, 1778-1852; Lewis, Tayler, 1802-1877; Loomis, Elias, 1811-1889; Mason, Cyrus, 1798-1865; Morris, Dewitt Clinton, 1821-1868; Parker, George S.; Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1815-1886; Tucker, Sarah, d.ca. 1859; Van Cleve, John Woodhull, 1812-1881; Van Name, Julia A. Gibbs, 1836-1916; Gibbs family; Johnson family; Van Cleef family; New York University
- E. A. JOHNSON, 1837-1891; Series I; 2.1' (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is divided into two sections, Personal Correspondence and Professional Papers. Personal Correspondence contains all letters written by and addressed to Ebenezer Alfred Johnson. All correspondence is arranged in chronological order and undated correspondence is placed last. Subject files follow undated correspondence and are arranged in alphabetical order.
  Professional Papers contain the materials that relate to Johnson's professional career and is in three parts. Correspondence arranged chronologically comes first, followed by printed materials filed chronologically, and finally by subject files arranged alphabetically.
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1838-1839, 1840 March-1845 Jul, 1845 September-1846 December (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
    - Correspondence, 1847 February-1848 Nov, 1849 January-1860, 1862, 1863 February-Jul, 1863 September-Oct, 1865-1869 (Box 2, Folder 23-50)
    - Correspondence, 1870-1875 Nov, 1876-1883, 1885-1889, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 51-76)
    - Correspondence: Sarah Bryan Johnson, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Correspondence: Mary Ann Johnson, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Correspondence: Ebenezer Alfred Johnson; Margaret (Van Cleve) Johnson; Harriet (Gilley) Johnson, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Correspondence: Frances Henrietta Johnson; Alfred Van Cleve Johnson, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Correspondence: Other Johnson; Mary Anna Gibbs, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Letter fragments, 1840, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Certificates, 1837, 1840 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Invitations, 1856-1891 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Professional Papers
    - Correspondence, 1839, 1841-1869 (Box 4, Folder 86-107)
    - Correspondence, 1870-1891, undated (Box 5, Folder 108-116)
    - Printed materials, 1837-1849, 1851-1889, undated (Box 5, Folder 117-120)
    - Article on Professor Johnson in University, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - University of the City of New York: faculty and council records, 1836-1888, undated (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - University of the City of New York: financial papers, 1846-1891 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - University of the City of New York: other papers, 1836-1857, undated (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - University of the City of New York: student lists, 1836-1837 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - University of the City of New York: student papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Yale University, 1863-1888 (Box 5, Folder 127)
- FAMILY PAPERS, 1760-(1830-1919) 1969; Series II; 3.3' (8 boxes)
  Series II is divided into six sections, Margaret Johnson, Harriet G. Johnson, Frances H. Johnson, Alfred V. C. Johnson, Other Johnson, and Van Cleve. Each section has the same arrangement. Correspondence is arranged chronologically, undated correspondence follows dated correspondence, and subject files arranged alphabetically follow undated correspondence.
  Margaret Johnson contains all correspondence to and from Margaret (Van Cleve) Johnson, except that between her and her husband, which is placed in Series I Personal Correspondence.
  Harriet G. Johnson contains all letters to and from Harriet (Gilley) Johnson, except the ones between her and E.A. Johnson and between her and Margaret (Van Cleve) Johnson. This principle continues throughout Series II.
  - Margaret Johnson
    - Correspondence, 1830-1837, 1838 February-1841 December (Box 6, Folder 128-144)
    - Correspondence, 1842 February-1844 Jun, 1844 August-1847 Dec, 1848-1849 (Box 7, Folder 145-158)
    - Correspondence from relatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Correspondence to and from friends, undated (Box 7, Folder 160)
    - Correspondence unknown, undated (Box 7, Folder 161)
    - Diary fragment, 1838 (Box 7, Folder 162)
    - Essays, 1833, 1838 (Box 8, Folder 163)
    - "The Floweret", 1832 (Box 8, Folder 164)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 8, Folder 165)
    - Religious exercises, 1834 (Box 8, Folder 166)
    - School papers, 1834-1835, undated (Box 8, Folder 167-170)
  - Harriet G. Johnson
    - Correspondence, 1833-1842, 1844-1845, 1847-1857, 1859-1865, 1867-1868, 1870-1878 Apr, 1878 June-Oct, 1879-1880 (Box 8, Folder 171-183)
    - Correspondence from relatives, undated (Box 8, Folder 184)
    - Correspondence to children, undated (Box 8, Folder 185)
    - Bethlehem Seminary certificate, 1834 (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Frances H. Johnson
    - Correspondence, 1854-1858, 1860-1869 (Box 8, Folder 187-190)
    - Correspondence, 1870-1871, 1872 February-1872 Sep, 1982 October-December, 1873-1874 Aug, 1874 October-Nov, 1875 February-1879 December (Box 9, Folder 191-210)
    - Correspondence, 1880 January-1901 (Box 10, Folder 211-235)
    - Correspondence, 1902-1907, 1909-1915, 1916 February-1920 (Box 11, Folder 236-247)
    - Correspondence from cousins, undated (Box 11, Folder 248)
    - Correspondence from Alfred Van Cleve Johnson, undated (Box 11, Folder 249)
    - Correspondence from Sarah Bryan Johnson, undated (Box 11, Folder 250)
    - Correspondence from other relatives, undated (Box 11, Folder 251)
    - Correspondence from friends, undated (Box 11, Folder 252)
    - Correspondence of Frances Henrietta Johnson, undated (Box 11, Folder 253)
    - Correspondence from unknown, undated (Box 11, Folder 254)
    - Calling cards and invitations, 1867-1919, undated (Box 11, Folder 255)
    - Diary fragment, 1870 (Box 11, Folder 256)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916, undated (Box 11, Folder 257)
    - Report card, 1856 (Box 11, Folder 258)
  - Alfred V. C. Johnson
    - Correspondence, 1857-1895, 1905-1906, undated (Box 11, Folder 259-261)
    - Essays, 1864-1865, undated (Box 11, Folder 262)
    - Journals, 1864-1878 (Box 11, Folder 263)
    - School papers, 1867, undated (Box 12, Folder 264)
    - Other papers, undated (Box 12, Folder 265)
  - Other Johnson
    - Correspondence, 1844, 1846-1857, 1860-1866, 1871-1879, 1881-1889, 1904, 1907, 1912, 1916, 1918, 1957, 1969, undated (Box 12, Folder 266-272)
    - "Ascent of Mount Etna, February 1832" by Sidney L. Johnson (Box 12, Folder 273)
    - Calling cards, undated (Box 12, Folder 274)
    - Cards, undated (Box 12, Folder 275)
    - Court case: Charles Andrew Johnson, 1847 (Box 12, Folder 276)
    - Diplomas, 1819, 1846 (Box 12, Folder 277)
    - Hall of Fame for Great Americans: Josiah Willard Gibbs, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 278)
    - Invitations, 1892, undated (Box 12, Folder 279)
    - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1856, 1921, undated (Box 12, Folder 280)
    - Money sent to New Haven by Johnson brothers in New Orleans, 1845-1857 (Box 12, Folder 281)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1838-1891, undated (Box 12, Folder 282-283)
    - Obituary: Charlotte (Johnson) Morris, 1851 (Box 12, Folder 284)
    - Pamphlets and articles, 1836-1957 (Box 12, Folder 285)
    - Pamphlets and booklets, 1856-1860, undated, 1855-1865, undated (Box 12, Folder 286-287)
    - School papers: William Codman, Jr., undated (Box 12, Folder 288)
    - United Society Church organ, 1822 (Box 12, Folder 289)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 12, Folder 290)
  - Van Cleve
    - Correspondence, 1781, 1796, 1818, 1821, 1825, 1827, 1831-1883 Oct, 1834-1836, 1839-1841, 1848-1849, undated (Box 13, Folder 291-304)
    - Bills: Louisa (Van Cleve) Daveiss, 1832-1834 (Box 13, Folder 305)
    - Diary of the Reverend Caleb Smith, 1760 January-June, 1761 February-June (Box 13, Folder 306-307)
    - Essays: Louisa (Van Cleve) Daveiss, 1835, undated (Box 13, Folder 308)
    - "The Floweret": Louisa (Van Cleve) Daveiss, 1829 (Box 13, Folder 309)
- FINANCIAL AND LEGAL, 1733-(1845-1891)1926; Series III; 1' (3 boxes)
  Series III contains both correspondence and subject files. The correspondence is in chronological order. Undated correspondence follows dated correspondence. Subject files are arranged alphabetically and follow undated correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1845-1856, 1858-1859, 1861-1869, 1871-1891, undated (Box 14, Folder 310-324)
  - Account book: E.A. Johnson, 1846-1853 (Box 14, Folder 325)
  - Account book: John Mott, 1859-1926 (Box 14, Folder 326)
  - Action of trespass, 1834 (Box 14, Folder 327)
  - Agreements, 1804-1876 (Box 14, Folder 328)
  - Bank receipts: Frances H. Johnson, 1892-1897 (Box 14, Folder 329-330)
  - Bank receipts: Frances H. Johnson, 1898-1906 (Box 15, Folder 331)
  - Bills: E.A. Johnson, 1856-1890 (Box 15, Folder 332)
  - Bonds, 1845-1884 (Box 15, Folder 333)
  - Business cards, undated (Box 15, Folder 334)
  - Cancelled checks: E.A. Johnson, 1869-1872 (Box 15, Folder 335-337)
  - Dauphin and Susquehanna Coal Co., 1854-1855 (Box 15, Folder 338)
  - Deeds: Ebenezer Johnson, 1799-1854 (Box 15, Folder 339)
  - Deeds: E.A. Johnson, 1855-1859 (Box 15, Folder 340)
  - Deeds: DeWitt C. Morris, 1853-1855 (Box 15, Folder 341)
  - Deeds: other, 1852-1855 (Box 15, Folder 342)
  - Deeds: copies, 1733, 1763 (Box 15, Folder 343)
  - Financial records: miscellaneous, 1849-1881 (Box 15, Folder 344)
  - Gibbs, Josiah W.: estate of, 1868 (Box 15, Folder 345)
  - Houston, Churchill: will, 1845 (Box 15, Folder 346)
  - Indentures, 1805-1875 (Box 15, Folder 347)
  - Insurance policies, 1852-1886 (Box 15, Folder 348)
  - Johnson, Charles Andrew: estate of, 1896 (Box 15, Folder 349)
  - Johnson, Ebenezer: estate of, 1861-1867 (Box 15, Folder 350)
  - Johnson, Laura (Mott); Johnson, Harriet, 1849-1885, undated (Box 15, Folder 351)
  - Johnson, Margaret (Van Cleve): estate of, 1849 (Box 15, Folder 352)
  - Judgment: E.A. Johnson, 1860 (Box 15, Folder 353)
  - Legal documents concerning sale of property to Frances H. Johnson, 1884-1889 (Box 15, Folder 354)
  - Maps: Frankford, Philadelphia County, Pennsylvania, 1853 (Box 15, Folder 355)
  - Morris, DeWitt C., 1849-1853 (Box 15, Folder 356)
  - Mortgages, 1845-1874 (Box 16, Folder 357)
  - Mortgages: assignments of, 1845-1850 (Box 16, Folder 358)
  - Notes, 1852-1878 (Box 16, Folder 359)
  - Power of attorney, 1871 (Box 16, Folder 360)
  - Receipts, 1853-1888 (Box 16, Folder 361)
  - Stock certificates, 1870 (Box 16, Folder 362)
  - Summons, 1852-1853 (Box 16, Folder 363)
  - Tax receipts, 1864-1890 (Box 16, Folder 364)
  - Title abstracts, 1884 (Box 16, Folder 365)
  - Woodlawn Cemetery, New York, 1881 (Box 16, Folder 366)
- GENEALOGY, 1878- (1878-1894) 1952; Series IV; .6' (2 boxes)
  Series IV contains correspondence arranged in chronological order and files on families studied by Charles Andrew Johnson, plus genealogical material on the Gilley and Van Cleve families. These genealogical files come after correspondence and are arranged alphabetically by family. Following the files on specific families, are files containing information on more than one family. These are arranged alphabetically by surname.
  - Correspondence, 1878-1894, 1952, undated (Box 17, Folder 367-376)
  - Baldwin family (Box 17, Folder 377)
  - Bryan family (Box 17, Folder 378)
  - Clark family (Box 17, Folder 379)
  - Gilley family (Box 17, Folder 380)
  - Johnson family (Box 17, Folder 381-383)
  - Typescript: "Robert Johnson and Some of His Descendants" (Box 17, Folder 384)
  - Johnson Family Ancestral Tablet (Box 17, Folder 385-386)
  - Johnson cemetery plot (Box 17, Folder 387)
  - Law family (Box 17, Folder 388)
  - Law family (Box 18, Folder 389)
  - Governor Jonathan Law funeral orations (Box 18, Folder 390)
  - Van Cleve family (Box 18, Folder 391)
  - Van Cleve family trees (Box 18, Folder 392)
  - Families A-E (Box 18, Folder 393)
  - Families F-M (Box 18, Folder 394)
  - Families N-W (Box 18, Folder 395)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, Series V; 0.5; (1 box)
  Series V contains around forty photographs, many of which are unidentified.
  - Photographs (Box 19)
  - 1824 Nov 22. Phillips, Elizabeth ALS to her aunt Louisa Anna (Houston) Van Cleve and her cousin Louisa E. Van Cleve. To this are added ALS from Mary Anna (Van Cleve) Gibbs to her brother and sister; ALS from Eliza Smith (Houston) Phillips to her sister Louisa Anna (Houston) Van Cleve; and ALS from Horatio Gates Phillips to Dr. John Van Cleve. (Box 20)